Contact

dehall2@verizon.net

www.linkedin.com/in/deborahhall-msn-mba-rn-ccns-cphqfache-438686a (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

ACLS

Nursing Healthcare

Certifications

Lean Six Sigma Green Belt FACHE

Certified Professional in Healthcare Quality (CPHQ)

CCRN Alumnus Status

CCNS Acute and Critical Care, Adult

Publications

The Trauma of Trauma: A Community Hospital Perspective

Concept to Reality: Integrating Technology in the Hospital Setting

Evaluation of a 16-Week Critical Care Internship Program Using a Staff Development Program Effectiveness Evaluation Tool

Deborah Hall, MSN, MBA, RN, CCNS, CPHQ, FACHE

Vice President, Quality & Patient Safety at University of Maryland Baltimore Washington Medical Center

Baltimore, Maryland Area

Summary

More than 25 years experience as a member of the nursing leadership team in acute care hospitals. As a nationally certified Clinical Nurse Specialist in acute and critical care, I possess a unique approach to nursing administration that encompasses strength in education, clinical consultation and administrative leadership. With more than 25 years experience at the bedside in critical care and experience in the role of formal nursing education, my strengths include the ability to develop cohesive and collaborative relationships with the staff and physicians, develop protocols and policies that are evidence-based, appropriate financial management and utilization of resources, and a strong voice for nursing to assure a healthy work environment. Demonstrated successes include the development and management of cost effective, cohesive clinical service lines related to acute and critical care environments. Core values include clinical excellence, service excellence and staff satisfaction.

Strengths include hospital regulatory compliance, nursing operations, evaluation and resrtucture of services provided.

Experience

University of Maryland Baltimore Washington Medical Center 6 years 7 months

Vice President, Quality & Patient Safety December 2016 - Present (3 years 8 months)

Director of Nursing, Acute Care January 2014 - December 2016 (3 years) Administrative responsibility for inpatient acute care units including all medical/ surgical units, progressive care, critical care, outpatient infusion and vascular access services, dialysis and inpatient wound care services.

Medstar Franklin Square Medical Center Administrative Director of Medicine Service Line January 2009 - December 2013 (5 years)

Administrative responsibility for inpatient acute care units including all medical/surgical units, critical care and Emergency Services. Service line encompasses approximately 650 FTEs.

Key contributer in strategic and operational planning and construction of a new patient care tower that opened in November, 2010.

Designed and implemented the merging of several medical/surgical and telemetry units including cost center changes, leadership and unit management models, and staff support for merging unit cultures.

Participated in successful implementation of Cerner EMR including nursing documentation, medication administration, specimen collection and CPOE. Designed and implemented a 24-bed observation unit requiring redesign of 2 tower units and developed operational plan for an 18-bed overflow unit; completed in a 4-week timeframe while remaining under budget for the project.

Participated in the planning, redesign, and operational implementation of an innovative monitor tech station with access to Real Time Location System and Teletracking.

Accomplishments:

Participated in strategic and operational planning for dialysis services resulting in change of vendor, budget planning and capital purchase of dialysis equipment.

Improved nursing efficiency through the revision of staffing and scheduling processes resulting in a salary cost reduction of greater than \$450,000. Gold Plus Award for consistent achievement of stroke quality measures. Identified and replaced high cost supply items in the clinical areas resulting in a cost savings of over \$400,000 in FY12.

Participated in the creation and submission of Magnet Re-designation document which was accepted for a site visit in May, 2013. Achieved Magnet Re-designation in July 2013.

Executive Sponsor of the Nursing Quality and Patient Safety Council.

Brandywine Hospital (CHS)

2 years

Assistant Chief Nursing Officer
July 2007 - October 2008 (1 year 4 months)

Directed operations and regulatory compliance for the Department of Nursing; approximately 350-400 FTEs.

Performed OB service line industry, market, and financial analyses and developed a revitalization plan and closure process.

Served as hospital champion for Quint Studer customer service model resulting in a decrease in call bells and improved patient and employee satisfaction.

Accomplishments:

Decreased ED LOS from 105 minutes to 60 minutes, increased recruitment from SON through improved communication process, and decreased director workload through process change.

Identified and replaced high cost supply items in the clinical areas resulting in an approximate cost savings of \$80,000.

Implemented an on-boarding process that resulted in improved retention in the first 90 days and a decrease in nursing turnover from greater than 25% to 15% in 3 quarters.

Decreased contract labor in nursing from 36 FTEs to 13 FTEs in 9 months

Director Critical Care Services
November 2006 - July 2007 (9 months)

Administrative responsibility for ICU, PCU and Telemetry.

Designed and implemented a staffing model and matrix, telemetry expansion, and cost analysis to merge a 30-bed Remote Telemetry/Medical Surgical Unit with a 26-bed PCU; potential revenue increase of \$4 million per year.

York College of Pennsylvania Adjunct Faculty, Department of Nursing January 2005 - May 2007 (2 years 5 months)

Clinical Instructor for senior level nursing students in acute and critical care areas including Medical /Surgical Leadership, ICU, Transitional Care Units, ED Taught Nursing Research to junior and senior level undergraduate students

Lancaster Regional Health System
Director of Critical Care and Critical Care CNS
February 1998 - October 2006 (8 years 9 months)

Held several positions throughout the 2 hospital health system including staff nurse in the ICU, Director of PCU, multisite Clinical Nurse Specialist for Emergency and Critical Care, Director of Critical Care Services

Deborah Heart and Lung Center Staff RN MICU 1988 - November 1997 (9 years)

Direct patient care for patients post PCI, open heart surgery, IABP, CVVH in the ICU setting

Medical Center of Ocean County Charge Nurse Coronary Care Unit 1981 - 1988 (7 years) 3-11 charge nurse for 10 bed Coronary Care unit

Education

Eastern University
MBA, Health Administration · (2007 - 2009)

Widener University
MSN, Emergency & Critical Care CNS · (2001 - 2003)

Monmouth University BSN, Nursing · (1992 - 1997)

Ann May School of Nursing RN Diploma, Nursing · (1977 - 1980)